{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This island's Great Tulip Tree in Inwood Hill Park was the site of a celebration commemorating Robert Fulton and a certain 1609 discovery. The Castello Plan, created by Jacques Cortelyou, mapped a portion of this island while under Dutch settlement. A large statue of King George III was pulled down on this island's Bowling Green park, and this island was purchased for New Netherland from the Canarsee by Peter Minuit. New Amsterdam was founded on, for ten points, what densely populated island in New York City?",
      "answer": "Manhattan Island"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two answers required: During a battle between these two countries, Raimondo Montecuccoli claimed, \"Today died a man who did honor to mankind” after that man was killed by a cannonball. The Barrier Treaties were signed by these two countries, one of which invaded the other during the Rampjaar [[RAMP-yahr]]. A conflict between these two countries that led to a number of peripheral conflicts was ended with the Peace of Nijmegen [[NYE-may-gen]] signed in one of them. For ten points, name these two countries which were respectively led by Louis XIV [[the Fourteenth]] and William of Orange.",
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of France and the Netherlands",
        "Holland",
        "Nederland in place of the “Netherlands”",
        "Royaume de France in place of Kingdom of France"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man served as governor of Cyprus before being elected tribune in 62 BC. This member of the Optimates was notoriously resistant to bribes and accused his rival of being a part of the Catiline Conspiracy. One anecdote from that rivalry involved this man publicly reading a love letter from his half-sister, Servilia. An opponent of the First Triumvirate, for ten points, who was this Roman senator and rival of Julius Caesar, the great-grandson of an orator known for ending speeches with the line, \"Carthage must be destroyed\"?",
      "answer": [
        "Cato the Younger or Cato Minor",
        "Marcus Porcius Cato Uticensis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "H.F. van Emden and David Peakall wrote a 1996 follow-up to this work titled: Beyond [this book]. This book was inspired by a letter appearing in The Boston Herald and credits declining bird populations to thin eggshells that broke prematurely. Al Gore credited this work with starting his interest in environmental issues, and this work was instrumental in the EPA's eventual ban on DDT for agricultural use. For ten points, name this best-selling 1962 environmental science book by Rachel Carson.",
      "answer": "Silent Spring 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a Dutch town, two members of this organization named Sigismund Best and Richard Stevens were captured during the Venlo Incident after a trap was sprung by Abwehr [[AHB-vehr]] head Walter Schellenberg. This organization plotted, but never executed, a plan to sneak estrogen into Adolf Hitler's food in an effort to feminize him. Author Graham Greene served in this organization under Kim Philby, who later betrayed this organization as a member of the \"Cambridge Five\" and joined the KGB. For ten points, name this foreign intelligence agency of the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": [
        "MI6",
        "Secret Intelligence Service",
        "SIS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man and his sibling used Frank Meyer's principle of \"fusionism\" when they developed the \"Sharon Statement,\" which was the guiding thesis of the Young Americans for Freedom. This man threated to \"sock a\" debate opponent \"in the mouth\" if he kept calling him a crypto-Nazi during a publicly televised debate. Leftist intellectual Gore Vidal debated, for ten points, what intellectual conservative and host of Firing Line who founded the National Review?",
      "answer": "William Frank Buckley, Jr."
    },
    {
      "question": "Between 1854 and 1855, three of these events named Tokai, Nankai, and Edo were collectively known as the Ansei. The military murdered an estimated 6,000 Koreans and socialists who they believed caused one of these events. Goto Shinpei led infrastructure projects following a 1923 example of these events, which mostly did not impact Frank Lloyd Wright's Imperial Hotel. For ten points, name these natural disasters that included the Great Kanto, which destroyed many buildings in Japan.",
      "answer": [
        "Earthquakes",
        "1923 Great Kanto earthquake"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first superintendent of an institution under this organization, Franklin Buchanan, defected to the Confederacy, and an academy run by this organization was established by George Bancroft. This organization's technology during the War of 1812 was analyzed in the first book by Theodore Roosevelt, who was this organization's Assistant Secretary. Alfred Thayer Mahan's time as an officer in this organization inspired his book The Influence of Sea Power upon History. For ten points, name this organization, which operates an Academy in Annapolis, Maryland.",
      "answer": [
        "United States Navy",
        "USN"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An anachronism in a film about this historical figure involved the appearance of a pair of purple Converse sneakers during a shopping spree. A musical by Michael Kunze and Sylvester Levay parallels the life of this historical figure with a woman named Margrid Arnaud. A 2006 film directed by Sofia Coppola portrayed this figure’s affair with Axel von Fersen. For ten points, what historical figure was the wife of Louis XVI [[the Sixteenth]] and last queen of France before the French Revolution?",
      "answer": [
        "Marie Antoinette or Marie Antoinette Josèphe Jeanne",
        "or Maria Antonia Josepha Johanna"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Geraldine Brooks's novel March analyses a father who has left to serve in this war as described in another book. Michael Shaara's The Killer Angels takes place during a battle in this war, a deserter from which is the subject of Charles Frazier's Cold Mountain. John Winder helped oversee a location used during this war in a novel by Mackinlay Kantor titled Andersonville. In a short novel, Henry Fleming overcomes his cowardice by seeking the title injury during this war. For ten points, name this war, the setting of The Red Badge of Courage.",
      "answer": [
        "American Civil War or United States Civil War",
        "or U.S. Civil War 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A photograph at Sri Lanka’s Palaly Airport shows this man being given a garland by an athlete. An anti-religion campaign may have led to the false attribution of a quote to this man in which he supposedly said that he “didn’t see any God” during his most famous undertaking. A MiG-15 crash killed this man, who once served at Luostari Air Base. This backup crew member of Soyuz 1 was best-known for a single 1961 orbit. For ten points, name this Soviet cosmonaut and first man in space.",
        "answer": "Yuri Gagarin or Yuri Alexeyivich Gagarin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Yuri Gagarin Cosmonaut Training Center is found in what space research facility named for an astronomical object?",
        "answer": "Star City"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While speaking with Morley Safer, this figure controversially revealed that she would not be surprised if her eighteen-year old daughter admitted to having an affair. That interview prompted this woman’s husband to say, “Well, honey, there goes about 20 million votes.” This prominent supporter of the Equal Rights Amendment co-founded a facility in Rancho Mirage for people suffering from drug addiction. Rising to her most prominent position in 1974, for ten points, who was this woman who succeeded Pat Nixon as First Lady?",
        "answer": "Betty Ford"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While Gerald Ford was in office, which man’s wife, “Happy,” served as Second Lady of the United States?",
        "answer": "Nelson Rockefeller or Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One member of this family wrote Geography Made Easy, which became one of the most influential geography textbooks in the early United States. A son of this family’s aforementioned member named Jedediah received guidance from Leonard Gale that allowed for his realization of a regular relay system to accomplish one task. The question “What hath God wrought?” was asked by a member of this family who developed the single- wire variant of a communications system. For ten points, what family included the telegraphy pioneer Samuel?",
        "answer": [
          "Morse",
          "Jedediah Morse",
          "Samuel Finley Breese Morse"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A minister who trained with Jonathan Edwards, Jedediah Morse gave three sermons promoting John Robison's book Proof of a Conspiracy which claimed what mysterious group was behind the French Revolution?",
        "answer": [
          "Illuminati",
          "Bavarian Illuminati"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Daniel E. Nijensohn did an analysis of this person’s skull x-rays and suggested that she was given a pre-frontal lobotomy months before her death. Thousands of people were injured when this person’s body was transported to the Ministry of Labour Building. This person’s corpse was found in a crypt in Milan, Italy under the name “María Maggi” after being lost for sixteen years following her husband's overthrow in the Revolución Libertadora. For ten points, name this wildly popular first lady of Argentina during the late 1940s and early 1950s.",
        "answer": [
          "Eva Perón or María Eva Duarte de Perón",
          "or María Eva Duarte",
          "Evita Perón"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What former president of Argentina and leading politician of the Peronist Justicialist Party said that she was inspired by Eva due to \"her example of passion and combativeness.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Cristina Fernández de Kirchner or Cristina Elisabet Fernández de Kirchner",
          "CFK"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With the Offields, this family established the Catalina Island Conservancy. The character Walter Harvey, in A League of Their Own, may have been inspired by a member of this family who founded the All-American Girls Professional Baseball League during World War Two. Charles Weeghman facilitated the sale of an organization to this family, which names a location containing a wall covered in ivy. The Steve Bartman incident occurred at a location named for this family of chewing gum magnates. For ten points, the Chicago Cubs play in what family’s namesake field?",
        "answer": [
          "Wrigley",
          "William Mills Wrigley Jr.",
          "Philip Knight Wrigley",
          "P.K. Wrigley",
          "Wrigley Field"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Chicago Cubs ended a 108-year World Series drought in what year, in which the Cleveland Cavaliers became the first NBA team to overcome a 3-1 deficit and the New England Patriots overcame a 28-3 deficit in Super Bowl LI [[Fifty-One]].",
        "answer": "2016"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A replication of one of this psychologist’s experiments used emails to study attitudes towards presidential candidate Ross Perot [[PEH-roh]]. The University of London replicated this psychologist’s experiment on altruism by leaving 300 letters on sidewalks. This psychologist asked, “Could it be that Eichmann and his million accomplices in the Holocaust were just following orders?” in a noted namesake experiment. For ten points, what psychologist tested obedience to authority through the administering of fake electric shocks?",
        "answer": [
          "Stanley Milgram",
          "Milgram experiments"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Milgram-led experiment studied the average path-length for social networks in the United States? Though Milgram never used the term, this experiment led to the phrase \"Six Degrees of Separation.\"",
        "answer": "Small-World Experiment 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s son, with Kathleen Bruce, founded the World Wide Fund for Nature. This man claimed that his group would “bow to the will of Providence” in a “Message to the Public.\" A line from Alfred, Lord Tennyson’s poem “Ulysses” was inscribed in a monument built for those lost during this man’s disastrous Terra Nova Expedition. That entry was written after this man’s team descended Beardmore Glacier during an effort in which he learned that Roald Amundsen had already reached the South Pole. For ten points, name this British explorer of Antarctica.",
        "answer": "Robert Falcon Scott"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Robert Falcon Scott also led what 1901 to 1904 expedition that launched the careers of several other explorers including Frank Wild, Edward Wilson, and Ernest Shackleton?",
        "answer": "Discovery Expedition"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Though not primarily known as a painter, this man created an oil work on canvas depicting The Ruins of Holyrood Chapel. Charles Marie Bouton [[boo-TOHN]] worked with this man who utilized “hypo,\" now known as sodium thiosulfate, to achieve a notable effect. In an attempt to increase his profits, this man discouraged his partner from revealing his father, Nicéphore Niépce's, method of creating heliographs. For ten points, identify this Frenchman who developed a namesake process of creating photographic images.",
        "answer": "Louis Daguerre"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Englishman, and author of The Pencil of Nature, got into an intellectual property dispute with Louis Daguerre over the invention of Daguerre’s photographic technique?",
        "answer": "Henry Fox Talbot or William Henry Fox Talbot"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Missouri",
      "prompt": "Concerning the state of Missouri, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Senator who guided the U.S. as president through the end of the Second World War.",
          "answer": "Harry S. Truman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kentucky congressman and Secretary of State who championed the Missouri Compromise.",
          "answer": "Henry Clay, Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian sect expelled from Northern Missouri resulting in their relocation to Nauvoo, Illinois.",
          "answer": "Mormons"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that was the point of departure for the Oregon and Santa Fe Trails.",
          "answer": "Independence, Missouri"
        },
        {
          "question": "Missouri native who was the last U.S. five-star general.",
          "answer": "Omar Nelson Bradley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massacre of pro-slavery Kansas settlers by a Missouri militia led by John Brown.",
          "answer": "Pottawatomie Creek Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of 19th century earthquakes named for a Missouri region which was used by Tecumseh to signal the start of a native revolt.",
          "answer": "New Madrid ] Earthquakes"
        },
        {
          "question": "One of the first two senators for Missouri, known as \"Old Bullion,\" the first man to serve five terms in the Senate.",
          "answer": "Thomas Hart Benton 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Basque Region",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Basque region of Spain and France, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Treaty named for a mountain range which split the region.",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty of the Pyrenees",
            "Tratado de los Pirineos"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City which holds a famed \"Running of the Bulls.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Pamplona",
            "Iruña"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Historical kingdom whose Henry III inherited France in the 16th century.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Navarre or Nafarroako Erresuma",
            "or Reino de Navarra",
            "or Royaume de Navarre",
            "Henry III, King of Navarre"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Minority, known as \"buhameak,\" who were treated as untouchables by locals and only allowed to marry within their culture.",
          "answer": [
            "Romani",
            "Gypsy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Separatist organization that blew up the car of Francoist general Luis Carrero Blanco.",
          "answer": "ETA or Euskadi Ta Askatasuna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Semi-mythological battle at which Roland prevented an ambush by Saracens in a French chanson.",
          "answer": "Battle of Roncevaux Pass"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Plan\" named for a leader proposing a free association of the Basque Country with Spain on an equal footing.",
          "answer": [
            "Ibarretxe ] Plan",
            "Political Statute of the Community of the Basque Country",
            "Juan José Ibarretxe Markuartu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"White Lord\" and mythical first king who was the son of an exiled Scottish princess.",
          "answer": "Jaun ] Zuria 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mexican War of Independence",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Mexican War of Independence, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country from which Mexico secured its independence.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Spain",
            "Reino de Espana"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor of France defeated at Waterloo whose invasion of Spain weakened their rule over Mexico.",
          "answer": [
            "Napoleon I",
            "Napoleon Bonaparte"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President and general who fought in the war before ordering mass executions at the Alamo.",
          "answer": "Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna or Antonio de Padua María Severino López de Santa Anna y Pérez de Lebrón"
        },
        {
          "question": "Priest who died in 1811 and was an early father of Mexican independence.",
          "answer": "Father Hidalgo or Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rallying cry by that priest that signaled the call to arms for the war.",
          "answer": "Cry of Dolores or Grito de Dolores"
        },
        {
          "question": "Independence leader and first emperor of Mexico who issued the Plan of Iguala.",
          "answer": [
            "Agustin de Iturbide",
            "Agustín I",
            "Augustine of Mexico"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Army that battled Royalist forces which identified as protecting \"religion, independence, and unity.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Army of the Three Guarantees",
            "Ejército de las Tres Garantías",
            "Trigarante Army"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Priest who became the first president of the \"Supreme Mexican Government.\"",
          "answer": "Jose Maria Morelos or José María Teclo Morelos Pérez y Pavón 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Student sympathizers of this movement were brutally massacred by the anti- leftist death squad known as Grupo Colina during the Barrios Altos Massacre. Strongman Francisco Morales-Bermúdez's call for open elections in 1980 was ignored by this political faction, who (20 pts)",
        "launched the \"People War\" in the Ayacucho region. The leader of this movement, Abimael [[ah-bee-MAH-ehl]] Guzman, was placed in a cage for public display after his capture by forces loyal to Alberto (10 pts)",
        "Fujimori. For ten points, name this Maoist guerilla movement-turned terrorist syndicate of 20th century Peru."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Shining Path",
        "Sendero Luminoso",
        "Communist Party of Peru before \"Peru\" is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Before this event, one group involved in it visited the Cattaraugus Reservation to gain insight into a particular group's societal position. During the second day of this event, Thomas McClintock read portions of Blackstone’s Commentaries on the Laws. During this event, (20 pts)",
        "Frederick Douglass advocated for the “ninth resolution.” Many of this event’s organizers went to the World Anti-Slavery Convention with William Lloyd Garrison. The Declaration of (10 pts)",
        "Sentiments was drafted as a result of this event. For ten points, Lucretia Mott and Elizabeth Cady Stanton organized what event to advocate for women’s rights?"
      ],
      "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A conflict named for this body of water was referred to as “the first serious nuclear crisis” by U.S. Secretary of State Christian Herter. The Dachen Islands were seized during a crisis named for this body of water. In 1950, a fleet was sent in by Harry (20 pts)",
        "Truman to “neutralize” this body of water. A third crisis was sparked after missiles were launched in this body of water under the supervision of Lee Teng-hui. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, what \"Strait\" surrounded the territorial disputes between the People’s Republic of China and the Republic of China?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Taiwan Strait",
        "Formosa Strait",
        "Strait of Fokien",
        "Strait of Fujian",
        "variations like Strait of Taiwan 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The speaker of this oration notes how “the life of the world may move forward into broad, sunlit uplands” if a certain result is achieved. This address's speaker warns that “the whole fury and might of the enemy must very soon be turned on (20 pts)",
        "us.” In this speech, the orator claims, “We in this Island…will never lose our sense of comradeship” and states that a certain sentiment would hold “if the empire lasts a thousand years.” Given two weeks after its speaker had noted that “we shall (10 pts)",
        "fight on the beaches”, for ten points, what was this speech by Winston Churchill about a certain glorious time period?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "“This was their finest hour\" speech",
        "Winston Churchill's speech on June 18, 1940 before the House of Commons"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) J.B. Vrients was sold a set of plates belonging to a work by Cornelis de Jode titled for the “Mirror of [this place].\" Rhumb lines were used in a 1569 depiction of this place that was itself inspired by a work known as “Theatre of [this place]\" by Abraham Ortelius. The “pocket” (20 pts)",
        "variety of one type of depiction of this place was popularized amongst elites in the 17th century. Many depictions of this place were made during the Golden Age of Flemish cartography, including the (10 pts)",
        "Mercator Projection. For ten points, name this planet depicted on atlases and globes."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The World or Earth",
        "Orbis Terrarum"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city was the origin of a movement of upper-middle class teenagers who came to admire American culture, the Swing Youth. The Star-Club is found in this city, where one group’s frequent performing caught the attention of Brian (20 pts)",
        "Epstein, who was later known as the “Fifth” member of that group. Between 1960 and 1962, the Beatles often performed in the Reeperbahn in this city located on the (10 pts)",
        "Elbe. For ten points, name this Northern German city."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Free and Hanseatic City of Hamburg",
        "Freie und Hansestadt Hamburg",
        "Friee un Hansestadt Hamborg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A temple to this deity was consecrated by Gaius Duilius after the Battle of Mylae. In Ovid’s Fasti, this deity describes himself as the “janitor of the celestial court.” Numa Pompilius established a temple at the forum that was dedicated to this deity. The (20 pts)",
        "rex sacrorum typically offered a ram to this deity during the Agonium festival. The opening and closing of the gates at this deity’s temple symbolized, respectively, (10 pts)",
        "wartime or peace. For ten points, who was this double-faced Roman god of beginnings and transitions?"
      ],
      "answer": "Janus or Ianus 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After moving to an all-white suburb of this city, Daisy Myers endured months of harassment before gaining the nickname \"Rosa Parks of the North.\" Henry Box Brown shipped himself to freedom in a crate to an Anti-Slavery (20 pts)",
        "Society in this city. John Africa founded the Black liberation group MOVE in this city. The Free African Society was called in to deal with a 1793 epidemic of yellow fever in this city, which was treated by Benjamin (10 pts)",
        "Rush. For ten points, name this city in which the Declaration of Independence was signed."
      ],
      "answer": "Philadelphia 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    }
  ]
}